<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Document><ExtractedText>1 
 
 
 
 
 
 
National Education  
Policy 2020 
 
 
 
Ministry of Human 
Resource Development 
 
Government of India 
 
1 
 
 
Chapter  Contents 
Page 
No 
 
Introduction 
3 
 
PART  I.  SCHOOL EDUCATION 
1 
 
Early Childhood Care and Education: The Foundation of Learning  
7 
2 
Foundational Literacy and Numeracy: An Urgent &amp; Necessary 
Prerequisite to Learning 
8 
3 
Curtailing Dropout Rates and Ensuring Universal Access to Education at 
All Levels  
10 
4 
Curriculum and Pedagogy in Schools: Learning Should be Holistic, 
Integrated, Enjoyable and Engaging 
11 
5 
Teachers 
20 
6 
Equitable and Inclusive Educa4tion: Learning for All 
24 
7 
Efficient Resourcing and Effective Governance through School 
Complexes/Clusters 
28 
8 
Standard-setting and Accreditation for School Education 
30 
PART II.  HIGHER EDUCATION 
9 
Quality Universities and Colleges: A New and Forward-looking Vision 
for India’s Higher Education System 
33 
10 
Institutional Restructuring and Consolidation 
34 
11 
Towards a More Holistic and Multidisciplinary Education 
36 
12 
Optimal Learning Environments and Support for Students 
38 
13 
Motivated, Energized and Capable Faculty 
40 
14 
Equity and Inclusion in Higher Education 
41 
15 
Teacher Education 
 
42 
16 
Re-imagining Vocational Education 
 
43 
17 
Catalyzing Quality Academic Research in all Fields through a New 
National Research Foundation 
45 
18 
Transforming the Regulatory System of Higher Education  
 
46 
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
2 
 
19 
Effective Governance and Leadership for Higher Education Institutions 
49 
PART III.  OTHER KEY AREAS OF FOCUS 
20 
Professional Education 
50 
21 
Adult Education and Life Long Learning 
51 
22 
Promotion of Indian Languages, Arts and Culture 
53 
23 
Technology Use and Integration 
56 
24 
Online and Digital Education: Ensuring Equitable Use of Technology 
58 
PART IV.  MAKING IT HAPPEN 
25 
Strengthening the Central Advisory Board of Education  
60 
26 
Financing: Affordable and Quality Education for All 
60 
27 
Implementation 
61 
 
List of Abbreviations used 
63 
 
 
 
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
3 
 
Introduction 
Education is fundamental for achieving full human potential, developing an equitable and just 
society, and promoting national development. Providing universal access to quality education is the 
key to India’s continued ascent, and leadership on the global stage in terms of economic growth, 
social justice and equality, scientific advancement, national integration, and cultural preservation. 
Universal high-quality education is the best way forward for developing and maximizing our 
country's rich talents and resources for the good of the individual, the society, the country, and the 
world. India will have the highest population of young people in the world over the next decade, and 
our ability to provide high-quality educational opportunities to them will determine the future of our 
country.  
The global education development agenda reflected in the Goal 4 (SDG4) of the 2030 Agenda for 
Sustainable Development, adopted by India in 2015 - seeks to “ensure inclusive and equitable quality 
education and promote lifelong learning opportunities for all” by 2030. Such a lofty goal will require 
the entire education system to be reconfigured to support and foster learning, so that all of the critical 
targets and goals (SDGs) of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development can be achieved.  
The world is undergoing rapid changes in the knowledge landscape. With various dramatic scientific 
and technological advances, such as the rise of big data, machine learning, and artificial intelligence, 
many unskilled jobs worldwide may be taken over by machines, while the need for a skilled 
workforce, particularly involving mathematics, computer science, and data science, in conjunction 
with multidisciplinary abilities across the sciences, social sciences, and humanities, will be 
increasingly in greater demand. With climate change, increasing pollution, and depleting natural 
resources, there will be a sizeable shift in how we meet the world’s energy, water, food, and 
sanitation needs, again resulting in the need for new skilled labour, particularly in biology, chemistry, 
physics, agriculture, climate science, and social science. The growing emergence of epidemics and 
pandemics will also call for collaborative research in infectious disease management and 
development of vaccines and the resultant social issues heightens the need for multidisciplinary 
learning. There will be a growing demand for humanities and art, as India moves towards becoming a 
developed country as well as among the three largest economies in the world. 
Indeed, with the quickly changing employment landscape and global ecosystem, it is becoming 
increasingly critical that children not only learn, but more importantly learn how to learn. Education 
thus, must move towards less content, and more towards learning about how to think critically and 
solve problems, how to be creative and multidisciplinary, and how to innovate, adapt, and absorb new 
material in novel and changing fields. Pedagogy must evolve to make education more experiential, 
holistic, integrated, inquiry-driven, discovery-oriented, learner-centred, discussion-based, flexible, 
and, of course, enjoyable. The curriculum must include basic arts, crafts, humanities, games, sports 
and fitness, languages, literature, culture, and values, in addition to science and mathematics, to 
develop all aspects and capabilities of learners; and make education more well-rounded, useful, and 
fulfilling to the learner. Education must build character, enable learners to be ethical, rational, 
compassionate, and caring, while at the same time prepare them for gainful, fulfilling employment. 
The gap between the current state of learning outcomes and what is required must be bridged through 
undertaking major reforms that bring the highest quality, equity, and integrity into the system, from 
early childhood care and education through higher education. 
The aim must be for India to have an education system by 2040 that is second to none, with equitable 
access to the highest-quality education for all learners regardless of social or economic background.  
This National Education Policy 2020 is the first education policy of the 21st century and aims to 
address the many growing developmental imperatives of our country. This Policy proposes the 
revision and revamping of all aspects of the education structure, including its regulation and 
governance, to create a new system that is aligned with the aspirational goals of 21st century 
education, including SDG4, while building upon India’s traditions and value systems. The National 
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
4 
 
Education Policy lays particular emphasis on the development of the creative potential of each 
individual. It is based on the principle that education must develop not only cognitive capacities - 
both the  ‘foundational capacities ’of literacy and numeracy and ‘higher-order’ cognitive capacities, 
such as critical thinking and problem solving – but also social, ethical, and emotional capacities and 
dispositions.  
The rich heritage of ancient and eternal Indian knowledge and thought has been a guiding light for 
this Policy. The pursuit of knowledge (Jnan), wisdom (Pragyaa), and truth (Satya) was always 
considered in Indian thought and philosophy as the highest human goal. The aim of education in 
ancient India was not just the acquisition of knowledge as preparation for life in this world, or life 
beyond schooling, but for the complete realization and liberation of the self. World-class institutions 
of ancient India such as Takshashila, Nalanda,Vikramshila, Vallabhi, set the highest standards of 
multidisciplinary teaching and research and hosted scholars and students from across backgrounds 
and countries. The Indian education system produced great scholars such as Charaka, Susruta, 
Aryabhata, Varahamihira,  Bhaskaracharya, Brahmagupta, Chanakya, Chakrapani Datta, Madhava, 
Panini, Patanjali, Nagarjuna, Gautama,  Pingala, Sankardev, Maitreyi, Gargi and Thiruvalluvar, 
among numerous others, who made seminal contributions to world knowledge in diverse fields such 
as mathematics, astronomy, metallurgy, medical science and surgery, civil engineering, architecture, 
shipbuilding and navigation, yoga, fine arts, chess, and more. Indian culture and philosophy have had 
a strong influence on the world.  These rich legacies to world heritage must not only be nurtured and 
preserved for posterity but also researched, enhanced, and put to new uses through our education 
system.  
The teacher must be at the centre of the fundamental reforms in the education system. The new 
education policy must help re-establish teachers, at all levels, as the most respected and essential 
members of our society, because they truly shape our next generation of citizens. It must do 
everything to empower teachers and help them to do their job as effectively as possible. The new 
education policy must help recruit the very best and brightest to enter the teaching profession at all 
levels, by ensuring livelihood, respect, dignity, and autonomy, while also instilling in the system 
basic methods of quality control and accountability. 
The new education policy must provide to all students, irrespective of their place of residence, a 
quality education system, with particular focus on historically marginalized, disadvantaged, and 
underrepresented groups. Education is a great leveler and is the best tool for achieving economic and 
social mobility, inclusion, and equality. Initiatives must be in place to ensure that all students from 
such groups, despite inherent obstacles, are provided various targeted opportunities to enter and excel 
in the educational system. 
These elements must be incorporated taking into account the local and global needs of the country, 
and with a respect for and deference to its rich diversity and culture. Instilling knowledge of India and 
its varied social, cultural, and technological needs, its inimitable artistic, language, and knowledge 
traditions, and its strong ethics in India’s young people is considered critical for purposes of national 
pride, self-confidence, self-knowledge, cooperation, and integration. 
Previous Policies 
The implementation of previous policies on education has focused largely on issues of access and 
equity. The unfinished agenda of the National Policy on Education 1986, modified in 1992 (NPE 
1986/92), is appropriately dealt with in this Policy. A major development since the last Policy of 
1986/92 has been the Right of Children to Free and Compulsory Education Act 2009 which laid 
down legal underpinnings for achieving universal elementary education. 
Principles of this Policy 
The purpose of the education system is to develop good human beings capable of rational thought 
and action, possessing compassion and empathy, courage and resilience, scientific temper and 
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
5 
 
creative imagination, with sound ethical moorings and values. It aims at producing engaged, 
productive, and contributing citizens for building an equitable, inclusive, and plural society as 
envisaged by our Constitution.   
A good education institution is one in which every student feels welcomed and cared for, where a 
safe and stimulating learning environment exists, where a wide range of learning experiences are 
offered, and where good physical infrastructure and appropriate resources conducive to learning are 
available to all students. Attaining these qualities must be the goal of every educational institution. 
However, at the same time, there must also be seamless integration and coordination across 
institutions and across all stages of education. 
The fundamental principles that will guide both the education system at large, as well as the 
individual institutions within it are: 
• recognizing, identifying, and fostering the unique capabilities of each student, by 
sensitizing teachers as well as parents to promote each student’s holistic development in both 
academic and non-academic spheres; 
• according the highest priority to achieving Foundational Literacy and Numeracy by all 
students by Grade 3; 
• flexibility, so that learners have the ability to choose their learning trajectories and programmes, 
and thereby choose their own paths in life according to their talents and interests;  
• no hard separations between arts and sciences, between curricular and extra-curricular 
activities, between vocational and academic streams, etc. in order to eliminate harmful 
hierarchies among, and silos between different areas of learning;  
• multidisciplinarity and a holistic education across the sciences, social sciences, arts, 
humanities, and sports for a multidisciplinary world in order to ensure the unity and integrity 
of all knowledge; 
• emphasis on conceptual understanding rather than rote learning and learning-for-exams; 
• creativity and critical thinking to encourage logical decision-making and innovation; 
• ethics and human &amp; Constitutional values like empathy, respect for others, cleanliness, 
courtesy, democratic spirit, spirit of service, respect for public property, scientific temper, 
liberty, responsibility, pluralism, equality, and justice; 
• promoting multilingualism and the power of language in teaching and learning; 
• life skills such as communication, cooperation, teamwork, and resilience; 
• focus on regular formative assessment for learning rather than the summative assessment that 
encourages today’s  ‘coaching culture ’;   
• extensive use of technology in teaching and learning, removing language barriers, increasing 
access for Divyang students, and educational planning and management; 
• respect for diversity and respect for the local context in all curriculum, pedagogy, and policy, 
always keeping in mind that education is a concurrent subject;  
• full equity and inclusion as the cornerstone of all educational decisions to ensure that all 
students are able to thrive in the education system;  
• synergy in curriculum across all levels of education from early childhood care and 
education to school education to higher education; 
• teachers and faculty as the heart of the learning process – their recruitment, continuous 
professional development, positive working environments and service conditions;  
 
• a ‘light but tight’  regulatory framework to ensure integrity, transparency, and resource 
efficiency of the educational system through audit and public disclosure while encouraging 
innovation and out-of-the-box ideas through autonomy, good governance, and empowerment; 
• outstanding research as a corequisite for outstanding education and development; 
• continuous  review of progress based on sustained research and regular assessment by 
educational experts;  
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
6 
 
• a rootedness and pride in India, and its rich, diverse, ancient and modern culture and 
knowledge systems and traditions; 
• education is a public service; access to quality education must be considered a basic right of 
every child;  
• substantial investment in a strong, vibrant public education system as well as the 
encouragement and facilitation of true philanthropic private and community participation.  
The Vision of this Policy 
This National Education Policy envisions an education system rooted in Indian ethos that contributes 
directly to transforming India, that is Bharat, sustainably into an equitable and vibrant knowledge 
society, by providing high-quality education to all, and thereby making India a global knowledge 
superpower. The Policy envisages that the curriculum and pedagogy of our institutions must 
develop among the students a deep sense of respect towards the Fundamental Duties and 
Constitutional values, bonding with one’s country, and a conscious awareness of one’s roles 
and responsibilities in a changing world. The vision of the Policy is to instill among the 
learners a deep-rooted pride in being Indian, not only in thought, but also in spirit, intellect, 
and deeds, as well as to develop knowledge, skills, values, and dispositions that support 
responsible commitment to human rights, sustainable development and living, and global 
well-being, thereby reflecting a truly global citizen.  
 
Part I. SCHOOL EDUCATION 
This policy envisages that the extant 10+2 structure in school education will be modified with a new 
pedagogical and curricular restructuring of 5+3+3+4 covering ages 3-18 as shown in the 
representative figure and elaborated in detail later under Chapter 4. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Middle 
10 
(Ages 6-16) 
2 
(Ages16-18) 
2 years 
(Class 1 &amp; 2)                
(Ages 6-8) 
.............……………… 
3 years  
(Anganwadi/ pre-
school/Balvatika)            
(Ages 3-6) 
3 
(Class 3 to 5) 
(Ages 8-11) 
3 
(Class 6 to 8) 
(Ages 11-14) 
4 
(Class 9 to 12) 
(Ages14-18) 
Previous academic structure 
New Pedagogical &amp; Curricular   Structure 
Foundational 
Preparatory 
Secondary 
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
7 
 
Currently, children in the age group of 3-6 are not covered in the 10+2 structure as Class 1 begins at 
age 6. In the new 5+3+3+4 structure, a strong base of Early Childhood Care and Education (ECCE) 
from age 3 is also included, which is aimed at promoting better overall learning, development, and 
well-being.  
1. Early Childhood Care and Education: The Foundation of Learning 
1.1. Over 85% of a child’s cumulative brain development occurs prior to the age of 6, indicating the 
critical importance of appropriate care and stimulation of the brain in the early years in order to 
ensure healthy brain development and growth. Presently, quality ECCE is not available to crores of 
young children, particularly children from socio-economically disadvantaged backgrounds. Strong 
investment in ECCE has the potential to give all young children such access, enabling them to 
participate and flourish in the educational system throughout their lives. Universal provisioning of 
quality early childhood development, care, and education must thus be achieved as soon as possible, 
and no later than 2030, to ensure that all students entering Grade 1 are school ready. 
1.2. ECCE ideally consists of flexible, multi-faceted, multi-level, play-based, activity-based, and 
inquiry-based learning, comprising of  alphabets, languages, numbers, counting, colours, shapes, 
indoor and outdoor play, puzzles and logical thinking, problem-solving, drawing, painting and other 
visual art, craft, drama and puppetry, music and movement. It also includes a focus on developing 
social capacities, sensitivity, good behaviour, courtesy, ethics, personal and public cleanliness, 
teamwork, and cooperation. The overall aim of ECCE will be to attain optimal outcomes in the 
domains of: physical and motor development, cognitive development, socio-emotional-ethical 
development, cultural/artistic development, and the development of communication and early 
language, literacy, and numeracy. 
1.3. A National Curricular and Pedagogical Framework for Early Childhood Care and Education 
(NCPFECCE) for children up to the age of 8 will be developed by NCERT in two parts, namely, a 
sub-framework for 0-3 year-olds, and a sub-framework for 3-8 year-olds, aligned with the above 
guidelines,  the latest research on ECCE, and national and international best practices. In particular, 
the numerous rich local traditions of India developed over millennia in ECCE involving art, stories, 
poetry, games, songs, and more, will also be suitably incorporated. The framework will serve as a 
guide both for parents and for early childhood care and education institutions. 
1.4. The overarching goal will be to ensure universal access to high-quality ECCE across the country 
in a phased manner. Special attention and priority will be given to districts and locations that are 
particularly socio-economically disadvantaged. ECCE shall be delivered through a significantly 
expanded and strengthened system of early-childhood education institutions consisting of (a) stand-
alone Anganwadis; (b) Anganwadis co-located with primary schools; (c) pre-primary 
schools/sections covering at least age 5 to 6 years co-located with existing primary schools; and (d) 
stand-alone pre-schools - all of which would recruit workers/teachers specially trained in the 
curriculum and pedagogy of ECCE. 
1.5. For universal access to ECCE, Anganwadi Centres will be strengthened with high-quality 
infrastructure, play equipment, and well-trained Anganwadi workers/teachers. Every Anganwadi will 
have a well-ventilated, well-designed, child-friendly and well-constructed building with an enriched 
learning environment. Children in Anganwadi Centres shall take activity-filled tours - and meet the 
teachers and students of their local primary schools, in order to make the transition from Anganwadi 
Centres to primary schools a smooth one. Anganwadis shall be fully integrated into school 
complexes/clusters, and Anganwadi children, parents, and teachers will be invited to attend and 
participate in school/school complex programmes and vice versa. 
1.6. It is envisaged that prior to the age of 5 every child will move to a “Preparatory Class” 
or “Balavatika” (that is, before Class 1), which has an ECCE-qualified teacher.  The learning 
in the Preparatory Class shall be based primarily on play-based learning with a focus on 
developing cognitive, affective, and psychomotor abilities and early literacy and numeracy. The mid-
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
8 
 
day meal programme shall also be extended to the Preparatory Classes in primary schools. Health 
check-ups and growth monitoring that are available in the Anganwadi system shall also be made 
available to Preparatory Class students of Anganwadi as well as of primary schools. 
1.7. To prepare an initial cadre of high-quality ECCE teachers in Anganwadis, current Anganwadi 
workers/teachers will be trained through a systematic effort in accordance with the 
curricular/pedagogical framework developed by NCERT. Anganwadi workers/teachers with 
qualifications of 10+2 and above shall be given a 6-month certificate programme in ECCE; and those 
with lower educational qualifications shall be given a one-year diploma programme covering early 
literacy, numeracy, and other relevant aspects of ECCE. These programmes may be run through 
digital/distance mode using DTH channels as well as smartphones, allowing teachers to acquire 
ECCE qualifications with minimal disruption to their current work. The ECCE training of Anganwadi 
workers/teachers will be mentored by the Cluster Resource Centres of the School Education 
Department which shall hold at least one monthly contact class for continuous assessment. In the 
longer term, State Governments shall prepare cadres of professionally qualified educators for early 
childhood care and education, through stage-specific professional training, mentoring mechanisms, 
and career mapping. Necessary facilities will also be created for the initial professional preparation of 
these educators and their Continuous Professional Development (CPD). 
1.8. ECCE will also be introduced in Ashramshalas in tribal-dominated areas and in all formats of 
alternative schooling in a phased manner. The process for integration and implementation of ECCE 
in Ashramshalas and alternative schooling will be similar to that detailed above. 
1.9. The responsibility for ECCE curriculum and pedagogy will lie with MHRD to ensure its 
continuity from pre-primary school through primary school, and to ensure due attention to the 
foundational aspects of education. The planning and implementation of early childhood care and 
education curriculum will be carried out jointly by the Ministries of HRD, Women and Child 
Development (WCD), Health and Family Welfare (HFW), and Tribal Affairs. A special joint task 
force will be constituted for continuous guidance of the smooth integration of early childhood care 
and education into school education.  
2. Foundational Literacy and Numeracy: An Urgent &amp; Necessary Prerequisite to Learning 
2.1. The ability to read and write, and perform basic operations with numbers, is a necessary 
foundation and an indispensable prerequisite for all future schooling and lifelong learning. However, 
various governmental, as well as non-governmental surveys, indicate that we are currently in a 
learning crisis: a large proportion of students currently in elementary school - estimated to be over 5 
crore in number - have not attained foundational literacy and numeracy, i.e., the ability to read and 
comprehend basic text and the ability to carry out basic addition and subtraction with Indian 
numerals.  
2.2. Attaining foundational literacy and numeracy for all children will thus become an urgent 
national mission, with immediate measures to be taken on many fronts and with clear goals that 
will be attained in the short term (including that every student will attain foundational literacy 
and numeracy by Grade 3). The highest priority of the education system will be to achieve 
universal foundational literacy and numeracy in primary school by 2025. The rest of this Policy 
will become relevant for our students only if this most basic learning requirement (i.e., reading, 
writing, and arithmetic at the foundational level) is first achieved. To this end, a National 
Mission on Foundational Literacy and Numeracy will be set up by the Ministry of Human 
Resource Development (MHRD) on priority. Accordingly, all State/UT governments will 
immediately prepare an implementation plan for attaining universal foundational literacy and 
numeracy in all primary schools, identifying stage-wise targets and goals to be achieved by 2025, and 
closely tracking and monitoring progress of the same. 
2.3. First, teacher vacancies will be filled at the earliest, in a time-bound manner - especially in 
disadvantaged areas and areas with large pupil-to-teacher ratios or high rates of illiteracy. Special 
 
 
National Education Policy 2020 
9 
 
attention will be given to employing local teachers or those with familiarity with local languages. A 
pupil-teacher ratio (PTR) of under 30:1 will be ensured at the level of each school; areas having large 
numbers of socio-economically disadvantaged students will aim for a PTR of under 25:1. Teachers 
will be trained, encouraged, and supported - with continuous professional development  - to impart 
foundational literacy and numeracy.  
2.4. On the curricular side, there will be  an increased focus on foundational literacy and numeracy - 
and generally, on reading, writing, speaking, counting, arithmetic, and mathematical thinking - 
throughout the preparatory and middle school curriculum, with a robust system of continuous 
formative/adaptive assessment to track and thereby individualize and ensure each student's learning. 
Specific hours daily - and regular events over the year-on activities involving these subjects will be 
dedicated to encourage and enthuse students. Teacher education and the early grade curriculum will 
be redesigned to have a renewed emphasis on foundational literacy and numeracy. 
2.5. Currently, with the lack of universal access to ECCE, a large proportion of children already fall 
behind within the first few weeks of Grade 1. Thus, to  ensure that all students are school ready, an 
interim 3-month play-based ‘school preparation module’   for all Grade 1 students, consisting of 
activities and workbooks around the learning of alphabets, sounds, words, colours, shapes, and 
numbers, and involving collaborations with peers and parents, will be developed by NCERT and 
SCERTs. 
2.6. A national repository of high-quality resources on foundational literacy and numeracy will be 
made available on the Digital Infrastructure for Knowledge Sharing (DIKSHA). Technological 
interventions to serve as aids to teachers and to help bridge any language barriers that may exist 
between teachers and students, will be piloted and implemented 
2.7. Due to the scale of the current learning crisis, all viable methods will be explored to support 
teachers in the mission of attaining universal foundational literacy and numeracy. Studies around the 
world show one-on-one peer tutoring to be extremely effective for learning not just for the learner, 
but also for the tutor. Thus, peer tutoring can be taken up as a voluntary and joyful activity for fellow 
students under the supervision of trained teachers and by taking due care of safety aspects. 
Additionally, it will also be made far easier for trained volunteers - from both the local community 
and beyond - to participate in this large-scale mission.  Every literate member of the community 
could commit to teaching one student/person how to read, it would change the country’s landscape 
very quickly. States may consider establishing innovative models to foster such peer-tutoring and 
volunteer activities, as well as launch other programmes to support learners, in this nationwide 
mission to promote foundational literacy and numeracy. 
2.8. Enjoyable and inspirational books for students at all levels will be developed, including through 
high-quality translation (technology assisted as needed) in all local and Indian languages, and will be 
made available extensively in both school and local public libraries. Public and school libraries will 
be significantly expanded to build a culture of reading across the country. Digital libraries will also 
be established. School libraries will be set up - particularly in villages - to serve the community 
during non-school hours, and book clubs may meet in public/school libraries to further facilitate and 
promote widespread reading. A National Book Promotion Policy will be formulated, and extensive 
initiatives will be undertaken to ensure the availability, accessibility, quality, and readership of books 
across geographies, languages, levels, and genres.  
2.9. Children are unable to learn optimally when they are undernourished or unwell. Hence, the 
nutrition and health (including mental health) of children will be addressed, through healthy meals 
and the introduction of well-trained social workers, counsellors, and community involvement into the 
schooling system. Furthermore, research shows that the morning hours after a nutritious breakfast can 
be particularly productive for the study of cognitively more demanding subjects and hence   these 
hours may be leveraged by providing a simple but energizing breakfast in addition to midday meals. 
In locations where hot meals are not possible, a simple but nutritious meal, e.g., groundnuts/chana 
mixed with jaggery and/or local fruits may be provided. All school children shall undergo regular 
</ExtractedText></Document>